# Yared Gebrie

# SQL Server/SSIS/SSRS/Power BI Developer & DBA

Phone: 206-353-2602 | Email: anbesie.yg@gmail.com | Seattle, WA GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/yaya2020130">https://github.com/yaya2020130</a> | Portfolio: <a href="https://yared10portfolio.herokuapp.com/">https://yared10portfolio.herokuapp.com/</a>

# **Professional Summary**

A certified SQL development professional with more than 6 years of database experience, A self-starter who is able to work independently and possess ability for critical thinking, analysis, strong verbal and written communication skills. I'm Team-oriented, technically motivated and creative, Strong inclination for finishing my job before the project deadline. Flexible and versatile to adapt to any new environment and work on any project.

#### Technical skills and tools

- Extensive Knowledge of Relational Database Management Systems and data warehousing Concepts; Conceptual, logical and physical data modeling, Data Mapping, ER Diagrams and Normalization.
- Experienced in Database Backup, Restore and Disaster Recovery procedures.
- Experienced in MS SQL Server installation, configuration, performance tuning, client/server connectivity, query optimization and running Database Consistency Checks using DBCC.
- Expert in providing high availability support for SQL Server: Database mirroring, log shipping, replication.
- Hands on experience in system security, managing user logins, granting access roles and creating services account.
- Creating Stored Procedures, Views, User Defined Functions, cursors, derived tables, indexes common table expressions (CTEs), Sub-Queries and Joins to facilitate efficient data manipulation and data consistency.
- Troubleshooting long running queries by using various methods including SQL Profiler, Database Engine Tuning adviser and third-party tool, DPA (Database Performance Analyzer) Solar winds.
- Proficient in Extracting, transforming and loading data from various heterogeneous data sources and destinations like Access, Excel, CSV, Oracle, flat files using connectors, tasks and transformations provided by SSIS.
- Experience in designing & developing, testing, and deploying reports such as Drill down, Drill through and parameterized reports sub reports, charts, Tabular, Matrix, Hyperlink and dashboard reports using SSRS (SQL Server Reporting Services)
- Experience in AGILE methodology, Scrum process and TFS (Team Foundation Server).
- Profound understanding of full Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC).
- Data modeling tools: TOAD, EDRAW, ERWIN
- BI tools: SSIS, SSRS, Power BI
- Cloud computing and other tools such as EC2, RDS, Visual Studio, etc.
- Front-end: HTML5, CSS, jQuery, Java Script, AJAX, Es6, REACT

- Back-end: SQL ,MYSQL, MongoDB, NoSQL ,Express Node , Handlebars, Node.js, Webpack, redux
- Other Tools: Heroku, Git, Visual Studio Code, WordPress, typescript

# **Work Experience**

# SQL Server/SSIS/SSRS/Power BI Developer 350Deschutes- Oregon ,WA

March 2018 to Present

- Modeling and reverse engineering fact and dimension tables as star/snowflake schema in data warehouse.
- Tuning and enhancing performance of expensive SQL queries and stored procedures.
- Normalizing and De-normalizing data for faster query retrieval.
- Performing complete Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC) process by analyzing business requirements and understanding the functional work flow of information from source systems to destination systems.
- Responsible for all aspects of ETL process using SSIS Including Creating, deployment and execution of the packages to move data from various sources to desired destinations.
- Creating various data processing tasks such as Execute SQL, Bulk insert, sequence and for each loop Containers using various transformation tools such as Fuzzy Lookups, Merge, Character map, Data conversion etc.
- Designing and Implementing ETL workflows, Event Handlers and Error Handling in SSIS packages.
- Analyze and perform data mapping by identifying source data field, target entities and lookup table ID's, with translation rules.
- Design ,develop and troubleshoot different tabular and parametrized SSRS reports.
- Perform various calculations using complex expressions in reports for various Output formats based on business requirement.
- Developing visual reports, dashboards and KPI scorecards using Power BI desktop.
- Proficient in making DAX queries in Power BI desktop.
- Creating tabular and multidimensional models that are compatible with warehouse standards using Power BI
- Create and maintain Technical documents.

# **SQL Server/SSIS/SSRS Developer**

### **Bridge IT Support-Alexandria, VA (Remote)**

August 2016 to March 2018

- Extensive working knowledge on managing and maintaining data warehouses.
- Managed day to day database maintenance operations, SQL server database backup-restore point in-time recovery, job scheduling in a real time production and lower environments.
- Implemented Transparent Data Encryption (TDE), Column-Level, Encryption, and Secure Sockets Layer encryption
- Expertise in creating and managing databases and users. Evaluating user permissions and granting access to authorized users using least privileges policy.
- Performed database migration from SQL server 2008/R2 to SQL Server 2012.
- Experienced in using data transformation such as derived column, Conditional Split, Merge, Union all, SCD, OLEDB command, etc.

- Troubleshooting and resolving database integrity, blocking and deadlocking.
- Performed defragmentation and rebuilding of indexes periodically on the production server
- Designed database maintenance plans to set up core maintenance tasks to make sure databases performs well, are regularly backed up in case of system failure and are checked for inconsistencies.

### **SQL Developer/DBA**

## Yasart Engineering plc. Addis Ababa ,Ethiopia

March 2013 to June 2016

- Write new and modify existing Complex Queries, stored procedures, Batch Scripts, dynamic SQL and Functions using Transactional SQL.
- Design, create, and deploy ETL processes using SSIS to extract ,transform, and load data in to different environments for incremental data load.
- Experience in transforming unstructured data from various data sources using SSIS Transformations; Conditional Split, Data conversion, Lookup, Merge Join ,Sort, OLEDB command and Derived Column for data cleaning and validation.
- Designing and Implementing ETL workflows, Event Handlers and Error Handling in SSIS packages.
- Write Parameterized stored procedures and functions necessary for generating Tabular reports and parameterized SSRS reports
- Design ,develop and troubleshoot different tabular and parametrized SSRS reports.
- Perform various calculations using complex expressions in reports for various Output formats as requested by users.
- Performed fine tuning of database objects and server to ensure efficient data retrieval.
- Implementation of SQL Principle, Securable, Permission, Roles and Authentication Modes as a part of Security Policies for various categories of users.
- Setting up and Monitored transactional replication, Database mirroring on different servers seated at different environments.
- Experience on configuring and maintaining automation strategies like Full backup, Transactional log backup, Differential backup and creating the maintenance plans for index optimization and index maintenance like index rebuild, index reorganize based on fragmentation.
- Installed and configured windows server failover clustering and successfully configure Always-ON Availability group for HADR (High Availability & Disaster Recovery) solutions.

#### **Education**

Degree: Bachelor's of Science in Mechanical Engineering, Addis Ababa University, Addis Ababa,

Ethiopia

**Certification:** Querying data with Transact- SQL

(https://courses.edx.org/certificates/4d0884f5dd3d4f2a84412534db503b85)

Certification: Full stack software developer ,University of Washington, Seattle

**Certification:** Engineer in training (EIT), Washington State

#### References

Will be provided upon request.